Okay, at long last it's time to talk
about the Civil War. And we ain't got no
time to waste. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. Okay, so we left off in the last
video with the secession of the southern
states after the election of Abraham
Lincoln. And at that point, the
Confederacy in the South was born. And
they were perfectly happy to enact the
divorce and live the rest of their days
in peace and slavery. But Abraham
Lincoln was not in fact content with
such an arrangement. He believed that
secession was a constitutional
impossibility. And therefore, he was
ready to do whatever it took to bring
those sassy and weward southern states
back into the Union. But ready and
committed as he was, Lincoln did not
relish leading the Union to fire the
first shot. And so that's when he put
his pondering pants on and all of a
sudden a solution presented itself. Oh,
by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Anyway, right here in South
Carolina was a federal fort called Fort
Sumpter. And let's not rush too quickly
past that because the details are
important. South Carolina was the first
to secede and that means it was very
much part of the Confederacy. But this
fort is controlled and staffed by
federal or union soldiers. And as it
turned out in April of 1861, these Union
troops needed fresh supplies of food and
munitions. And that's when the light
bulb over Lincoln's head went off and he
decided to send Union ships to resupply
the fort. And so at that point, the
president of the Confederacy, Jefferson
Davis, had a decision to make. On one
hand, the South's whole strategy was
simply to be left alone. On the other,
it just wouldn't do to have a
functioning Union fort staffed with
Union soldiers within Confederate
territory. Therefore, Davis made the
decision to fire on the Union ship and
apply pressure to the soldiers within
the fort. And two days later, the Union
soldiers surrendered, but now that shots
had been fired, Lincoln had all the
justification he needed to prosecute a
war against the Confederacy and attempt
to save the Union. And well, you know,
that's exactly what he did. So, look, I
hate to be the guy who spoils the ending
of something, but here's where I tell
you that the Union won the war. And
sorry if you didn't already know, but
honestly, where you been? Anyway, the
point is when the war began, it was in
no way clear that the Union would win
because each side had their distinct
advantages and disadvantages. And we'll
break those down into three categories.
First, let's consider population. Now,
the advantage here was for sure toward
the Union. I mean, the northern
population was almost five times as
large as the Confederate population
since it was home to the biggest cities
in the US, while the Confederacy was
mainly agricultural and not as densely
populated. And in case you yourself have
never prosecuted a war, let me tell you
that having more people to throw in
front of enemy gunfire is always a big
advantage. Okay, second, let's talk
economics. Now, the Union was home to
the vast majority of the United States
economic resources, including banks and
factories and railroads. And all of that
combined meant that it would be easier
for the North to continue paying for the
war as it dragged on. However, despite
that advantage, we cannot forget about
King Cut. You see, the South still
generated enormous wealth by growing and
exporting cotton both internationally
and domestically. And that actually was
a massive advantage for them. And why
says you? Well, says I, powerful states
like Great Britain and France depended
heavily on the export of southern
cotton. And that meant Confederate
leaders might be able to use that
dependence to secure an alliance against
the Union. And as we'll see in the next
video, unfortunately for them, that did
not work out. And finally, third, let's
talk about leadership. Now, in the
beginning of the war, Confederates had
by far the more talented generals. You
had generals like Robert E. Lee and
Thomas Stonewall Jackson who were
brilliant and decisive and scored early
victories for the South. I mean, the
guy's nickname was Stonewall, and I
think that'd be enough to make the Union
lines poop their pants. Anyway, part of
the advantage Confederate generals had
is that they were fighting a defensive
war, which meant that they had shorter
supply lines and held kind of a
homefield advantage against the invaders
from the north. Anyway, in contrast,
Lincoln up in the north for sure had
general problems. Like, none of his
generals seemed to act as aggressively
and decisively as Lincoln wanted. And as
a result of their timidity, the war just
dragged on and on. However, by the end
of the war, Lincoln appointed Ulisses as
Grant as general of the Union armies.
And at long last, here was a general who
was ready to butcher those rebellious
southerners. Okay, so each side had
their advantages and disadvantages, but
both the North and the South waged total
war against the other. And by
definition, a total war describes a
conflict in which combatants leverage
all the resources of their economies and
societies to secure victory in the
conflict. In other words, in total war,
it doesn't matter if you're a soldier or
woman on a farm or whatever, everyone
had to contribute in their own way to
victory. Now, certainly in the
beginning, both sides thought that this
would be a quick war if they made the
right strategic moves. I mean, look at
these people right here. These were
picnickers who came out to watch the
first major battle of the war because
they thought it would be kind of cute
and a good way to pass the afternoon.
But it was a blood bath and so were many
of the following battles. And that
convinced both sides that this would be
a long and protracted war. And the
longer the war stretched, the more it
became clear that total war was the only
option. Now, probably the most
widespread manifestation of total war
was the introduction on both sides of a
military draft, which legally required
men in a certain age range to fight in
the conflict. However, the success of
the draft was very different in the
South and in the North. In the South,
the Confederate draft was always facing
problems. And I'll mention two of the
most significant. First, remember the
Confederacy drafted a constitution that
majored heavily on states rights because
they were still saucy about the
concentration of federal power in the
United States. And so, while that whole
states rights thing was great for
protecting slavery, it was in fact not
great for fighting a war since the
Confederate government had very little
constitutional power to compel men to
fight. And that meant some men simply
ignored the draft and that weakened the
Confederate effort over time. But the
second problem was the inequality of the
draft. You see, the draft law allowed
for the exemption of one white planter
for every 20 enslaved people he owned.
And that was mainly to keep the southern
economy strong during the war because
without the planters, King Cotton might
be demoted to Prince Cotton or horror of
horrors, Duke cotton. And that was
unthinkable. But then in addition, the
law allowed a drafted man to pay a fee
in order to hire a substitute to fight
in his place. And so these policies
became a real problem for the
Confederacy because it meant that the
rich folk could avoid the war while the
poor were forced to fight to preserve
the wealth of the elite. Now the union
also implemented a draft law and it was
certainly more successful on account of
the greater centralized power in the
federal government. However, like the
south, this law faced resistance as
well. So the union draft law also had
provisions for wealthy men to pay for
substitutes and that caused similar
resentment. And the union had plenty of
draft dodgers as well, but in the north
it was handled a little different. You
see, Lincoln had already gone full hog
into his executive power and suspended
habius corpus, which is a constitutional
guarantee that citizens must be told why
they're being arrested. I mean, it's a
good thing on principle to know why
you're being arrested, but it also
really slows down the process of arrest
in order to make sure everything is
above board. So, he had done this in
response to mob action in Maryland when
angry crowds tried to obstruct Union
troops from traveling. And so, in
response, Lincoln justified suspending
this constitutional guarantee because
these mobs were interfering with
national security and because Congress
was not in session at the time. Anyway,
back to those who tried to evade the
draft. Lincoln didn't have time to hab
anyone's corpus. He had a war to win.
And so Lincoln authorized the arrest of
something like 15,000 draft dodgers and
southern sympathizers who were
undermining the Union war effort.
However, that use of federal power also
caused some resistance as well. In 1863,
mostly Irish immigrants rioted for 5
days in what became known as the New
York City draft riots. And the reasons
for this violent uprising are tied to
several themes that we've already
touched in this unit. You see, although
many of the Irish in New York had become
citizens and had become somewhat
successful in winning local political
offices, nivists lashed out against them
with constant and demeaning racial
insults and resistance. Also, it was
1863 and that was the year Lincoln
issued the Emancipation Proclamation,
which freed all the enslaved population
in the Confederacy. And I'll tell you
all about that in the next video, but
for now, you just need to realize that
the Irish working class resented it
because it meant that more free black
people would be competing for their
jobs. And finally, due to the provision
in the draft law that allowed wealthy
men to pay for a substitute, these
working-class Irish who could not afford
such a substitute grew all kinds of
resentful. And so that resentment boiled
over into a riot that began as a
resistance to the draft law, but quickly
turned into a race riot in which crowds
directed their violence against black
New Yorkers. And the riots were only
quelled once Lincoln sent federal troops
to New York, fresh off the battlefield
in Gettysburg. Okay, like I said
earlier, the Union won the war, even
though in the beginning that was not for
sure the certain outcome. So let's
finish by considering the three reasons
for the Union victory. First, you've got
improvements in leadership and strategy.
So recall that I said earlier that the
Confederates for sure had the better
generals in the beginning of the war and
that was on full display in the first
battle of Bull Run in 1861. And by the
way, the Confederates call this the
Battle of Manasses, but it's the same
thing, so you know, don't get confused.
Anyway, this was the first major battle
of the war and it also happens to be the
battle I mentioned earlier that
attracted all the picnickers looking for
some good entertainment. Anyway, Lincoln
hoped that by securing a quick victory
in the Confederate capital of Richmond
that the war would be over in a matter
of weeks. And while Union General Irvin
McDow did strike a hard blow, the
Confederate army responded with
unexpected force which sent Union
soldiers fleeing into Washington. And so
this battle proved to Lincoln that the
strength of the Confederacy was not to
be underestimated. And it also squashed
whatever hopes he had about bringing the
war to a quick end. But more
importantly, it began Lincoln's long
process of appointing and replacing
generals whom he felt were incompetent
to match the skill of their Confederate
counterparts. However, a general leading
Union forces in the West, namely Ulissiz
S. Grant scored a major victory in 1863
that gave Lincoln hope that he had found
a leader who could win the war for the
Union. And one of those major victories
was the siege of Vixsburg. So a vital
part of Lincoln's strategy was to
control the Mississippi River, but a key
Confederate fort at Vixsburg prevented
it. And so Grant executed a nearly
two-month siege at the fort and in the
end 29,000 Confederate soldiers
surrendered. And that victory secured
the Mississippi River for strategic
Union use and achieved Lincoln's goal of
cutting the Confederacy in half. And as
it happened, the victory at Vixsburg
coincided with the Union victory at
Gettysburg, which was a significant
turning point in the war, which turned
the tide in favor of the Union. And as a
result, Lincoln called Grant back east
and promoted him to become the general
of all the Union's armies. And related
to this was the second reason for Union
victory, namely the North's greater
resources. So a key part of Grant's
strategy moving forward was to fight a
war of attrition, meant to cut off
Confederate supplies and wear them down
until fighting became an impossibility.
And owing to the Union's superior wealth
and population and industry, a war of
attrition was a viable strategy.
Additionally, as the war dragged on,
southern morale waned significantly
because of the increasing hardships that
they were facing. You see, many
southerners resented the Confederate
government, which they felt was both
overstepping its authority and at the
same time not doing enough to address
the suffering of the Confederate
population. For example, in 1863, a
series of bread riots broke out in
several states across the Confederacy on
account of people couldn't afford basic
provisions to feed their families. And
that was due to many factors like outofc
control inflation on prices and an
increasing amount of food being sent to
feed troops. Therefore, rioting broke
out which was initially led by women and
the mobs looted grocery stores in order
to find bread and other basic
necessities. And so all in all, the
riots communicated that a good number of
Confederate citizens believed that their
government was neglecting their needs
and that had a way of seriously
deflating support for the Confederate
cause. And then the third reason for
Union victory was its strategy to
destroy southern infrastructure. The
most infamous example being Sherman's
march to the sea. So in order to fully
demoralize and incapacitate the South,
Grant sent General William Tecumpsa
Sherman to invade and capture Atlanta,
which was a major railroad hub for the
Confederacy. And as Sherman marched his
army from Chattanooga to Atlanta, he
commanded his men to employ a scorched
earth strategy, which is to say, he told
them to destroy everything in their
path. And when they got to Atlanta,
Sherman's troops fought and defeated
Confederate armies after a protracted
siege and then went ahead and set the
city on fire. Now, it was a devastating
loss for the South, and it meant that
transporting troops and supplies by rail
will become infinitely more difficult.
But as it turns out, Sherman was hungry
for a little more destruction. And so he
proposed to Grant that his men march
from Atlanta to Savannah while
continuing to deploy their scorched
earth strategy. So Grant approved and
the march destroyed vital food supplies
and railroads required by the
Confederates. And there are so many
other examples I could give you that
illustrate all the reasons for Union
victories, but that's going to do for
our purposes. Now, the war finally came
to an end in 1865 when Grant gained
control of a strategic railroad junction
in Virginia and then cut off the
Confederate army's escape route. And
after that, General Lee knew without a
doubt that the South was defeated. And
so he met Grant in the Appamatics
Courthouse in Virginia and formally
surrendered and the war was over. Well,
okay, you can click here to watch my
other videos for unit 5 or you can click
here to grab my video note guides which
are going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly grounded
to your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. Heimler out.